<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Edwards pen no slander: or, The Gangræna once more searched: which being found very full of corrupt matter, that part of his foul mouth is seringed, and washed with a moderate answer, given by Tho: Web, to that part of his book, wherein Mr. Edwards chargeth him for delivering severall Antinomian doctrines. In which answer is proved, that many things wherewith Mr. Edwards chargeth him, is false. Also, that Mr. Edwards charging any in such a nature is contrary to rule, and against all examples in Scripture, and tends unto division in these distracting times. / By Thomas Webbe.</title>
            <author>Webbe, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1206</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E337_34</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200835</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861468</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159706</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96140)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E337[34])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Edwards pen no slander: or, The Gangræna once more searched: which being found very full of corrupt matter, that part of his foul mouth is seringed, and washed with a moderate answer, given by Tho: Web, to that part of his book, wherein Mr. Edwards chargeth him for delivering severall Antinomian doctrines. In which answer is proved, that many things wherewith Mr. Edwards chargeth him, is false. Also, that Mr. Edwards charging any in such a nature is contrary to rule, and against all examples in Scripture, and tends unto division in these distracting times. / By Thomas Webbe.</title>
                  <author>Webbe, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Jane Coe, and are to be sold by Henry Overton, at his shop in Popes-Head Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Edwards, Thomas.  Gangræna (Wing E228).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Edwards, Thomas, 1599-1647. --  Gangræna --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antinomianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian sects --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159706:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Edwards Pen NO SLANDER: OR, The <hi>Gangraena</hi> once more ſearched: Which being found very full of corrupt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that part of his foul Mouth is ſeringed, and waſhed with a Moderate Anſwer, given by THO: WEB, to that part of his Book, wherein Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> chargeth him for delivering ſeverall <hi>Antinomian Doctrines.</hi> In which Anſwer is proved, that many things wherewith Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> chargeth him, is falſe. ALSO, That Mr. EDWARDS charging any in ſuch a nature is contrary to Rule, and againſt all Examples in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and tends unto diviſion in theſe diſtracting times.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS WEBBE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 COR. 16.14.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let all your things be done in Charity.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 COR, 13.8.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>For we can do nothing againſt the Truth, but for the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>EPHES. 4.31.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let all bitterneſſe, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evill ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, depart away from you, with all malice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Verſ. 32.</bibl> 
                  <hi>And be ye kind one to another, forgiving one another, even as God for Chriſts ſake hath forgiven you.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Jane Coe,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Henry Overton,</hi> at his Shop in Popes-Head Alley. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:159706:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159706:2"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> Pen no Slander.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is my hearts grief that I am engaged, to uſe my Pen, in matters that requires a publik ſatisfaction, in anſwring of M.
<hi>Edwards;</hi> but in as much as I apprehend, that its the will of God, I am ſatisfied, and am willing to give him an Anſwer: though I am altogether unwilling, that hatred ſhould naſwer hatred, and malice malice; but that love may give M. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> his hatred, a ſweet and Chriſtian-like Anſwer, and that in much patience: Alſo, that truth may appear for me, and not my ſelf (who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires nothing more then the braces of Peace &amp; Truth) in anſwering of M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> that part of his
<hi>Gangraena,</hi> wherein he charges me with many things; and where withall he ſeekes, not onely to take away my good name, but (alſo) againſt all Chriſtianity, my lively-hood. O that we could but live, anſwering <hi>Pauls Bowels of Compaſſion,</hi> ſweetly in a Chriſt-like love one towards another.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> is pleaſed to begin thus, (ſpeaking of me by name) he ſaith, that I was charged before the Honourable Houſe of Lords, for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering blaſphemous Doctrines, which (he ſaith) I have recanted of: this is his firſt Charge.</p>
            <p>Its true indeed, that I was before the Houſe of Lords; but I wonder, and its ſomthing ſtrange, that I ſhould recant of thoſe blaſphemous doctrines, when indeed, as unto me they were read, I did not own them: Its true, there was many Doctrines read over unto me, by the Clerk of the Lords Houſe, which would admit of dangerous and blaſphemous Conſtructions, &amp; were of dangerous conſequences; indeed quite contrary unto my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or opinion: but I having liberty to declare my ſelf concerning them before that Honourable Houſe; I did both to the Houſe, and to thoſe worthy Miniſters of the Synod, who were appointed to examine me; and as I thought did give good ſatisfaction, as did appear by my releaſement out of Priſon (onely there did remain a little money buſineſſe.) Now if this were a recantation, I refer it to wiſe judicious conſiderations.</p>
            <p>But grant it were a recantation, I had then whereof, not to be aſhamed but to glory, in reſpect of mercy ſhewed me, in recanting of them; but is it not againſt common reaſon, that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſhould divulge the ſame <pb n="2" facs="tcp:159706:3"/> in publique, to the rendring of me odious to the world, and bereaving me of my lively-hood, which that he doth in taking away my good name, which as the wiſe-man ſaith, is better then great abundance of worldly riches, as by ſad experience is wofully witneſſed: would it be a point of wiſdome for a Father, if that after his Son ſhould confeſſe his fault, and turn from it, that his Father ſhould declare the ſame to the world, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his Child were rendred odious, and thereby loſt his good name: O let in this caſe common reaſon ſtand between Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> and my ſelf.</p>
            <p>Secondly, grant that I had recanted of ſuch ſad blaſphemous doctrines, O what cauſe of rejoycing; and it had been his duty to a praiſed God for it on my behalf, knowing that praiſe waiteth for God in
<hi>Syon.</hi> God waits to do us good, and to be mercifull unto us, and we ſhould wait to praiſe God and to let paſſe no opportunity, nor receive no mercy, but praiſe ſhould be given forth to God: But how doth Mr.
<hi>Edwards</hi> wait upon God, as for every beame of love to praiſe God, who ſends forth the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious beames thereof to the Sons of men, when he in his writing vents nothing but ſelf and hatred, in the rendring me odious to the world, as if my recantation had bin an errour, and ſo the things of which I did recant were truth. Certainly, he was very zealous, but not according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; for knowledg would (as I conceive) have taught him otherwiſe (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to have praiſed God with me on my behalf) for convincing of me of thoſe dangerous and blaſphemous doctrines, there being no work of God. But what (of us all) worthy of all praiſe, but more eſpecially the work of God, which to us is one of the greateſt miracles wrought by divine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer (even the turning of a ſoule from errour unto truth) knowing, that the not knowing of God, and the way of God, in a true manner, or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel way, doth deprive the ſoule of many ſweet and precious enjoyments of God, and Goſpel priviledges, (alſo) that he that turneth a ſoule from ſinne, ſaveth it from Hell. O that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> would take it, and ſeriouſly conſider of it, whether he be greater then the Angels in Heaven; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pride be greater in him then in them: for certainly one of theſe muſt be, in as much as there is great joy amongſt them, over one ſinner that turns from his way: Now if they ſtoop down to us poor Creatures, ſo as to rejoyce at our returning from ſin unto God (oh why ſhould not Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi>) (nay) and how doth God himſelf embrace and provide a fatted Calf for his prodigall Son, that returns home unto him? now if ſo be, I have bin a prodigall Son (as indeed in ſome meaſure I have been) and have fed upon husks (which he tearms blaſphemous Doctrines) and at laſt I have turned, or God hath drawn me from them to truth, O what cauſe is here of Mr.
<hi>Edwards</hi> embracing of me, and taking me into his love and favour, ſeeing that God hath done it before him? but how doth he praiſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159706:3"/> God (nay he is) though in love I write it, as truly I muſt be plaine, in his wayes, farr below God in his wayes; for God embraces and ſweetly buſſes that ſoule that turnes to him, and provides a fatted Calfe for the poore ſoule ſweetly to feede upon; but he is ſo farre from em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing of me, that he ſeekes not only to make me odious to himſelfe, but alſo to the world; &amp; he is ſo farre from providing a fatted Calfe, as that if he could I feare he would provide for me; a leane and poore price, and a ſower and bitter bite, as doth appeare by his writings; and not only for me, but for the precious Elect and beloved ones of God, that are not in every thing of his judgement, truly, I could heartily wiſh that we were all of one heart and one minde, prayſing, and rejoyſing in the Lord; but ſeeing its not ſo, nor neither I nor Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> can tell how to fulfill our wills therein, and indeed as I may ſo ſay, its not the will of God ſo to have it as yet, O why ſhould he or any murmure againſt the hand of God herein, or envy thoſe who are not in every thing of his Judgement? or why ſhould he ſeeke to render them odious unto the world (whom I am confident neither he nor any can ſay are odious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God) a moſt ſad thing to cenſure of, and that which would if rightly applyed, draw blood from the heart; as it hath done by many precious ones, and indeede is below the protection the perfection of Saints; for that leades them to walke in wayes they know and do agree in, and if in any thing they be otherwiſe minded, God will reveale that unto them, here is now perfection, and a Goſpel ſpirit; but now Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> is ſo farre from this perfection, and walking this Goſpel path, that he neither exhorts, or ſeeks to walke with any, that with him in every thing doth not agree; nor yet praiſe God with me on my behalfe, who as he writes, hath recanted of former blaſpheamies, wherein confident I am, we did diſagree; which implyes both want of Knowledge, and want of Love; want of Knowledge in that he knowes not what the duty of one Chriſtian is to another, when there is a Chriſtian convinced of his error (nay) this is a great duty towards God; becauſe that when we praiſe God, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of one converted; we do therein advance God, and as in duty we are bound, declare his workes, which for his Saints he workes in <hi>Syon,</hi> holding him forth to the ſoules convincer.</p>
            <p>Secondly it implies want of love, that if he knew what were his Chriſtian duty, want of love to carry him forth to performe his duty towards any, even the leaſt and meaneſt of all Saints. Its true, I am a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to him, and he to me; yet not ſo ſtrange but we believe each other to be Chriſtians, now if he had, had any love towards me, or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, it would have carried him forth to have acted the acts of Chriſtianity, or if he had not believed me to be a Chriſtian, <pb n="4" facs="tcp:159706:4"/> yet knowing that love to all, and prayers for all, is acceptable with God, true love would for Gods ſake a carried him forth, to act towards me or any above himſelfe, or may infirmities; true love <hi>John</hi> ſaith, caſts out feare; even ſo it caſts out of the ſpirituall ſoule truly loving all declinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the contrary, and drawes it to live above its own glory, or ſelfe, and the weakneſſes of others in love with them; as Luther ſaith, in Chriſt and in his fellow-Saints, out of ſelfe, as ſelf in them, ſweetly as theirs: O if this were our practiſe one towards another, then would we praiſe and joy in the Lord, for the behalfe one of another.</p>
            <p>But me thinks I heare ſome friends in the Lord ſpeak, in the behalfe of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> his practice (ſaying) how could he do any otherwiſe then he hath done? when as he ſaith, I have ſince my recantation been in <hi>Suffolk, Eſſex,</hi> and <hi>Kent,</hi> venting
<hi>Antinomian</hi> doctrines.</p>
            <p>O let the Sons and friends of <hi>Syon</hi> judge, whether if I had vented ſince my recantation <hi>Antinomian Doctrines,</hi> it were a ſufficient reaſon for his practice, when as I never from him did receive any brotherly or friendly admonition; and the Scripture ſaith, that if thy Brother treſpaſſe, thou ſhould not preſently tel it the Church, till after twice or thrice admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but how doth he trace this Goſpell-path? when without any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhment he divulges me to the world; a moſt ſad thing, that he who profeſſes himſelf to be a Goſpell Miniſter, ſhould not, nor doth not himſelf tread Goſpel-paths, but he himſelf is a tranſgreſſour thereof. Truly, if I may herein be judge, I conceive, that if rightly conſidered of, it makes much againſt him, and that becauſe of my recantation, as he calls it; for if ſo be that I had recanted of Doctrines blaſphemous, then I conceive it was an Argument ſufficient enough to cary him forth, as followeth <hi>(viz.)</hi> not as his Brethren did, but in a brotherly manner to have informed me of the erroneouſneſſe of thoſe (nameleſſe) <hi>Antinomian Doctrines,</hi> which as he ſaith, I have vented; for if his Brethrens information cauſed me to recant, then ſurely it will appear to any reaſonoble man, that their expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of my wilingnes not only to heare their information; but alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſame, would have been to any reaſonable man, a ſufficient Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to have cauſed him to have informed me (not with a priſon) but in a Goſpel way, to have opened to me, the miſtery of the Scripture; whereby I might have been brought to a true underſtanding thereof, and to have ſeene the erroneouſneſſe of thoſe <hi>Antinomian</hi> doctrines, and how farre they come ſhort of truth, and are deſtructive to truth, and I in the end might ſweetly a been brought; to live in the enjoyment of Truth; which indeed my ſoule much hungers after.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it would have been an Argument conducing, to have cauſed him to have left his brotherly &amp; Saint-like information with me in the <pb n="5" facs="tcp:159706:4"/> will of God, and he himſelfe patiently to have waited in prayer at the throne of Grace; that his brotherly information might have wrought upon me, (knowing) that that God, that cauſed me to recant of thoſe blaſpheamous doctrines; remaines ſtill the ſame God, and is now as able, if he pleaſe to inable me recant of the Antinomian doctrines alſo, and ſo he and I might ſweetly have fed upon the diſcovery of divine miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and I through the ſame, might have been brought to leave and ſay farwell to all things that are contrary to ſound doctrine.</p>
            <p>But truly I feare, and therefore I mourne, that he is a ſtranger to this life of Goſpel-living, to this life of Saints (but no wonder, its a hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, &amp; ſo a miſterious life) as it appears, for where there is one petition put up to God, either for me, or thoſe who are ſtiled Independents, there is ten to one, put up to God and the Parliament againſt us, for our ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; but here is mine and their comfort, that though through our weakneſſes we may be baniſhed out of his and other mens favour, yet they cannot baniſh us out of Gods favour, and though he mourne and murmure at our being implyed in offices for the State, and ſo may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade us of the ſame, yet his murmurings cannot degrade us of that which is the all glory, even of dwelling in, and injoying all ſpirituall bleſſings, in heavenly places, here is joy full of glory, and I doubt not but this honour will remaine, let him do what he can (even the worlds reading and ſpelling out of Chriſt in our bookes, when it may not in his.)</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> in his booke writes, that I have been in
<hi>Eſſex, Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,</hi> and <hi>Kent,</hi> where I have vented Antinomian doctrines, its true I have been in theſe three Counties, but for venting
<hi>Antinomian:</hi> doctrins, that I am ignorant of; but I humbly deſire Mr.
<hi>Edwards,</hi> that if he writes againe, he would be willing to explaine what he meanes by <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomianiſme,</hi> and where my doctrine was ſuch, for <hi>Suffolk</hi> he names not the particulars of my doctrine, it may be, its becauſe he knowes them not, or if he doth know, its becauſe it was againſt covetuouſneſſe, but it ſeems by the ſtory, that what doctrine ſoever it were, its called by him <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianiſme</hi> (well) but if to ſet up Chriſt, and to beat downe covetuouſneſſe, be ſo, I did do it, and I hope God will ſtill carry me forth ſo to do, and the Scripture I there ſpake from, was Act. 5.11. and if there be man or woman that can charge me with delivering <hi>Antinomians</hi> doctrins, I in a brotherly manner deſire to be informed.</p>
            <p>And he ſaith further, that I would have taught in publike, if the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter had not hindred me; ſurely his informer is fe'd, well, which makes him to informe him any thing, its no matter whether they be true or falſe, any thing to pleaſe children; for while I was in <hi>Suffolk</hi> which, was not a week, I taught foure tymes, twice on the Lords day, and twice
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159706:5"/> the Wedneſday following which was the faſt day, and not once in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, the Townes name is <hi>Stocke,</hi> neere <hi>Clare</hi> in
<hi>Suffolk,</hi> nor was I hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by any Miniſter, as he writes, nor was there any one Miniſter in the Countie that was moved to let me teach, and the Towne wherein I was, was then deſtitute of a Miniſter.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Eſſex</hi> he ſaith, I taught in one Mr.
<hi>Sparrowes</hi> houſe of <hi>Colcheſter</hi> againſt all baptiſm, truly ſeverall times I did ſpeak in the ſaid houſe, and being occaſioned, through the diſpute of ſome honeſt people that are under baptiſm, touching the ſame, and I being engaged in the ſame diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, did deliver my ſelfe as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Scripture puts a difference between the baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> and the baptiſm of <hi>Chriſt; Johns</hi> being of water, and <hi>Chriſts</hi> being of the Holy Ghoſt, according as is witneſſed by theſe inſuing Scriptures, <hi>Math</hi>
3.11.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſm which was water, did end at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, as <hi>John</hi> 3.30. and that becauſe it manifeſted a Chriſt to come unto <hi>Jſrael,</hi> who being already come, is ceaſed. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.31. which I having premiſed, I gave out my thoughts; that there muſt be a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond inſtitution of baptiſm with water, or elſe it is not of that weight, as many of our friends take it to be, which inſtitution I read not of in any part of the New Teſtament; I meane, that CHRIST in his perſon did not inſtitute the ſame, as I reade of; And in <hi>Matth. Chapt.</hi> the 28. where my friends conceive that CHRIST did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute that Ordinance of water which they practice, I conceive it may as well be applied to any other Baptiſme as that of the holy Ghoſt, as to water, the Text not naming of water; yet notwithſtanding I did not then, nor do I now deny the practice of it; onely as I ſaid then, ſo I ſay now; by way of exhortation deſiring thoſe my friends not to make ſuch a diviſion about it, knowing that neither circumciſion nor uncircumciſion availeth any thing, ſave onely the Baptiſme of the holy Spirit, which is the New-creature, intreating of them to look more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſaid baptiſme, and then would our diviſions about the former ceaſe; and we being baptized by one Spirit into one Body, ſhould ſweetly live in and to one another, as members of one body: Now thoſe my friends that were then preſent could not give me ſatisfaction, in proving Baptiſme with water to be inſtituted by Chriſt, or in any part of the New Teſtament was given forth by him, while perſonally upon earth to his Apoſtles; And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>He was not ſent to Baptize, but to preach;</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. But if Mr.
<hi>Edwards</hi> will be pleaſed to appear in the proving of it, I ſhall much praiſe God for it, and ſhall acknowledge him to be my Father in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:159706:5"/>A ſecond thing which Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> writes I delivered in the ſaid houſe is, That a Saint may ſay he is equall with Chriſt, and count it no robbery. I could wiſh with all my heart, that he would (if it had been an errour) have done God ſo much ſervice, as to have diſproved it; I was ſpeaking out of <hi>Joh.</hi>
7.22. the words are there; <hi>The glory which thou gaveſt me I have given them, that they may be one, even as thou Father and I am one.</hi> From theſe words, after ſome time ſpent, in ſhewing what this glory was in the generall, I came to the particulars or draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it out in branches; and the firſt was, <hi>Gods love the ſame unto the Saints as unto Chriſt;</hi> which I proved by many reaſons, which now I ſhall not name: but there being amongſt many Scriptures, one very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to the thing, I named it; which is, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23. <hi>Thou hast loved them as thou haſt loved me.</hi> Chriſt ſets forth the Fathers love to the Saints, by the Fathers love to him, <hi>as thou haſt loved me:</hi> I opened this word <hi>(as)</hi> wherein lieth much, which is not now my buſineſſe, onely I humbly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat Mr.
<hi>Edwards,</hi> that if he judge it to be an errour, that he would prove it ſo to be, for he leaving a thing neither proving nor yet diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of it to be a truth, makes me with many, think that he believes it to be a truth, but would not have the Saints to know of it, or elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the world not being to judge of ſuch things, but is ready to ſpeak evill of dignities (even of what they know not) he preſents it them, that ſo I might become the more odious and vile in their ſight, and truly if it be an errour, as I deſire him to prove, I ſhall leave it, reioycing in the Lord, for his love in taking me off from it. But blame me not if I ſtill remain in the ſame judgement, having (as I conceive) the Word of God to be my rule, provided I meet with a fair &amp; candid interpretation of my words, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.
<hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.17. But if God by any ſhall give me forth an underſtanding of theſe Scriptures, which is contrary to what I bring them for, I am one who am not willing to withſtand truth, but deſire to be overcome by truth in every thing, though it come but from the hands of the pooreſt creature under heaven, whoſe Scholler I am ready to be, when ever God ſhall teach me any thing by him.</p>
            <p>A third thing which Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> charges me withall, is how that I being talking with an honeſt Chriſtian in <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> ſhould uſe this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; <hi>That it was not lawfull to ſay God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the Holy Ghoſt, for then there were three Gods;</hi> and it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of me, whether I ſpake this as my judgement, or onely for Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument ſake? But I was ſilent.</p>
            <p>It's my delight to converſe with <hi>Zions</hi> lovers, and indeed many I did converſe withall while I was at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> but not to any of them did I ſo deliver my ſelf, ſo that I am charged falſly; nor indeed is it, or ever <pb n="8" facs="tcp:159706:6"/> was it my judgement: but I truly believe God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the Holy Ghoſt, and yet but one; taking the ſaid God (that is the father) to be both Sonne and Holy Ghoſt, and ſo but one God, though God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the Holy Ghoſt; a myſterie, which at this time is not my work to unfold.</p>
            <p>A fourth Charge is, how that I ſhould ſay, <hi>That I had other points to ſpeak of to them, but there was a Wolf crept in among the Fold;</hi> (indeed Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> was then at <hi>Colchester</hi>) but at that time I knew it not, nor did I uſe ſuch an expreſſion, nor had I my thoughts of him at that time, but a guilty conſcience is a great matter, inſomuch as what it ſpeaks, the man thinks that all knows it, even as Thieves take Trees for men; but if I had ſpoke thoſe words, what would it afford him, if he were to ſell it at the beſt rate? Sure I am that if I had, I had but ſpoke the truth for he would have had me complained of; but he met with few ſuch ſpirits as himſelf, God be thanked for it, for the Shepheard (Chriſt) will not ſuffer his ſheep to be a prey to the Wolf (perſecution) therefore to Him be honour and glory in the Church.</p>
            <p>Now is it not a ſad thing, that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſhould receive a ſword to fight againſt the anointed of the Lord, and not know wether he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it from the hand of truth, and with the ſame ſword cauſe the anointed to bleed, pricking them with it as if it were the ſword of the Spirit, received by him at the hands of Truth; when indeed and in truth its neither, but a Jewiſh Spear: The infirmities of the Saints is not that ſword by which the Spirit fights, no it's the Word of God, and prayer, that ſword alone which Goſpell Miniſters ſhould fight withall againſt the Saints infirmities, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17. Nor is any other ſword gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the hand of Truth to Goſpell Miniſters, ſave onely the Word of God,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 10.10. and <hi>Chapt.</hi> 28. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17. With which ſwords they are to fight againſt, not the Saints neither, but their infirmities; was it not a Jewiſh Spear wherewith the Jews fought againſt Chriſt? (even his infirmities) but they found none, but ſuch as they call'd infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities? Even ſo, how Jewiſhly do men fight againſt the Kings Sonnes, when they take their infirmities, nay ſuch as they call infirmities, to fight againſt them withall? Truly my heart bleeds within me to conſider of it, and in beholding of the Kings Sonnes, lying ſome beaten, ſome woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſome ſlain by the Kings ſervants, well may we call for mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed, when that Miniſters the Kings ſervants, ſhall kill and ſlay the Saints, the Kings Sonnes, with a Spear: Oh what heart cannot but break to ſee this?</p>
            <p>Had it been an infirmity in me to have ſaid, I have many things to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat of, but a Wolf is crept in among the fold, when Chriſt himſelf gives <pb n="9" facs="tcp:159706:6"/> it as a caution to his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi>
10.16,17. <hi>Behold I ſend you forth as Sheep amongst Wolves, be ye therefore as wiſe as Serpents, and innocent as Doves. Beware of men, for they will deliver you up to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and they will ſcourge you in their Synagogues, &amp;c.</hi> Nay and it was the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> ſtill to beware of ſuch; amongſt them that are perfect, declare I the things of God in a miſterie, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. And ſee how he withſtood the falſe Brethren, that would have brought <hi>Paul</hi> in bondage in the uſe of his liberty, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.3. So truly, it's both Mr. <hi>Edward's</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and mine to beware of Wolves.</p>
            <p>But I praiſe God, I did not uſe ſuch an expreſſion, not becauſe the expreſſion is not good, but becauſe thoſe people that credit all for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell which Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> writes, may ſee the contrary, and ſo be humbled for it; For truly to my grief, I heat many of all ſorts, <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> as well as others, cry out of his Book, ſaying, <hi>That where there is one true tale, there be twenty and ten falſe ones;</hi> and the parties, as many as I have ſpoken with who are therein mentioned, are ſad to think that he ſhould be ſo farre blinded, as to be lead to ſpeak evill of thoſe, who cordially love the truth, and deſire to love him as themſelves.</p>
            <p>A fifth Charge is, <hi>How that upon November laſt I was talking with a Citizen, and told him, that the golden Calf, the Scriptures was faln, and I hope that all would be Anabaptiſts, and ſo be of my judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's ſtrange, and unto me a contradiction, that I ſhould ſo ſpeak to a nameleſſe Citizen, and yet my ſelf an earneſt ſeeker after the knowledge of the ſame, and deſire to walk in every thing according to the Scripture: Nay further, that I ſhould hope they would be all Anabaptiſts, when as they fetch no ground for their practice, out of any thing but Scripture: Now that I ſhould be a well-willer to theſe, and yet deny Scripture, is a meer contradiction. And truly I ſpeak the truth, I do with an unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned deteſtation utterly deteſt againſt it, or any opinion that ſhall lead me to the queſtioning of the truth of Scripture, in the leaſt meaſure, and am ſo farre from denying of it, as that when ever God ſhall be pleaſed to call me to it, I am willing to lay down my life for the truth of it.</p>
            <p>In his ſixth Charge, Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> alſo ſpeaks of my being in <hi>Kent; Where</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>I vented Antinomian Doctrines:</hi> but he doth not tell the particulars of it, ſo that I cannot give him a particular anſwer; onely this, if to teach Faith and Repentance be
<hi>Antinomianiſme,</hi> then I taught it: But he writes, how that in the Town of <hi>Milton</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> I taught for the Miniſter thereof, and in my ſecond and third Sermon, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered ſtrange <hi>Antinomian</hi> doctrines, ſo that a 150. of the people would not hear me, and that there was two complaints made to the Juſtices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, whereupon they would not let me live in the County: alſo <pb n="10" facs="tcp:159706:7"/> that I ſhould ſay it were better for a man to ſit and be drunk in an Ale-houſe, then to be compelled to go to Church againſt his conſcience.</p>
            <p>Truly, I am by Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> ſo ingaged to appeare in publike, as that I cannot appeare; but that will appeare with me which I know by ſome will not be well accepted of: and truly its much againſt my nature; to err any otherwiſe then to bury all the infirmities (of the infirmiſt) but ſeeing I muſt put penn to paper, I receive this charge into 3. heads, as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt is, that in my ſecond and third Sermon I delivered ſtrange <hi>Antinomian:</hi> doctrines &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Its true I taught certaine times for Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> by name, their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter there, and three Sermons I taught in his hearing, which by him, was not excepted againſt, but was very well approved of, as will appear by ſufficient witneſſes, if required; and for what I taught in his abſence, it was no waies contradicting, or diſagreeable with what I taught in his preſence, and if there were a hundred and fifty (which was but ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) that did abſent themſelves from hearing of me, I challenge all or any of them, to diſprove by Scripture, or argument, what I delivered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, or any for them, (Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> if he can) for truly I am not afraid, that what I delivered ſhould be brought to the touchſtone, Gods word, there to be tryed by any; but what if there had been a hundred and fifty, that had abſented themſelves from hearing of me, it would not follow, that what I taught was <hi>Antinomianiſme,</hi> nay if I or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould judge the Presbyterian way, by that rule, it would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by all, to be the Antichriſtian way; for confident I am, that there is none; of many of the Presbyterian Miniſters, but the better part of their pariſh abſent themſelves from hearing of them, againe ſure I am, that if any did abſent themſelves from hearing of me, if Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> ſpeak the truth to me, they did no more by me then they did by him; his word was there that I ſhould not be troubled at it, for they did ſo by him, and that his oppoſers were the great ones, and indeed if <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianiſme</hi> was the cauſe (as alas poore people they do not know what it is) they had as much cauſe to abſent from hearing of him, as from hearing of me, he teaching as much <hi>Antinomianiſme</hi> as I taught.</p>
            <p>The ſecond head is, that two complaints was made againſt me to the Juſtices, ſo that they would not let me live in the County.</p>
            <p>Firſt, what complaints were made againſt me, that I am ignorant of, but as I underſtand by one who was intimate with one of the Juſtices, they were ſuch complaints, as could not without ſhame to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playner be mentioned to me; the Juſtices words were theſe, that Mr.
<hi>Symonds</hi> then Miniſter at <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lton,</hi> ſhould depart the place, in as much as that he made ſeverall complaints to him againſt me, but when I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared he could ſay nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:159706:7"/>Secondly, there came forth a warrant from the Juſtices to the Boſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Milton;</hi> for the bringing of me before them, the warrant to my beſt remembrance was to this effect. That whereas <hi>Thomas Web</hi> living in the Towne of <hi>Milton,</hi> hath both in publike and private vented erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doctrines, to the diſhonour of God, to the deſtruction of all religion, and vilifying of civill Magiſtrates; Theſe are to require you, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A moſt ſtrange warrant, and I a moſt ſtrange perſon, as the Juſtices here hath formed me; if that mentioned in the warrant could be proved againſt me; but ſee the ſtrangeneſſe of men, I did appeare before the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, according to their warrant, expecting to have heard a charge, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what was expreſſed in the warrant, and to know my accuſers, which was but reaſonable, and being called into the roome where the Juſtices was, and two miniſters inſtead of giving me a lawfull charge ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what the warrant did expreſſe, Juſtice <hi>Hindrick</hi> by name, would have asked me queſtions; but I refuſing to anſwer, he tould me I had divided the Towne of <hi>Milton,</hi> I deſiring to know my accuers, he told me the ſecond time, that I had taught falſe doctrine. I ſtill deſiring to ſee my accuſers, inſtead of naming any, alſo inſtead of giving me a charge according to the nature of the warrant, the ſaid Iuſtice
<hi>Hindrick</hi> charges me with things, which was but my opinion delivered in private; As firſt, that I ſhould ſay that Magiſtrates had no power in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and his Chriſt. The ſecond was, that I ſhould ſay, That a Miniſter of the Goſpel, if caſt among the Jews to teach the Goſpel, his liberty was, to ſuffer his Converts to be circumciſed, for the Goſpel ſake, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Timothy.</hi> Now if herein I had juſtice and honeſt dealing, let any man judge; when as I by a warrant from the Juſtices was apprehended, in which I was charged as you may read; and at my appearance before them, ſhould be charged with that for er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, which was but the uſe of my liberty, as a free-born Denizon of
<hi>England</hi> (even my opinion to certain Queries in private) not doctrinal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered, but meerly by way of opinion; if herein I had juſtice let any judge. Nay herein I ſuffered much wrongfully, in as much as the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant appearing with ſuch ſad charges, did tend much to my hurt in ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring me odious to many honeſt and religious people, when as nothing was nor could be proved againſt me whereby I did juſtly deſerve it, but ſome ſhort time after my appearance, though nothing could be proved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, the ſame Juſtices iſſued forth another Warrant, for my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Town within ten dayes after the ſight thereof. A ſhort warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and indeed a ſad ſentence, when I had my Wife lying on her Bed of ſickneſſe, in ſuch a weak manner, as none thought ſhe would ever have riſen out of her Bed; but if the queſtion ſhould be demanded of me, why
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:159706:8"/> this cruelty (as it can be tearmed no leſſe) was uſed? Truly, for my part, I cannot give a ſufficient anſwer, nay I muſt be ſilent for I cannot tell only as I may judge, it was a zeal without knowledge, and will without a love was the reaſon of it; This Mr.
<hi>Edwards</hi> mentions, as if ſo be I left the County through the ſaid Warrant; truly I would have him to know, that I would not give an Arbitrary Government ſo much footing in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and it's well known to all in the Town; Firſt, that I was in the Town, three Weeks after the ten dayes were expired; and ſecondly, that I had not ſtirred out of the Town upon ſo ſlight tearms, but would have had juſtice done on one ſide or other had I not through the perſwaſions of ſome friends in <hi>London,</hi> removed my wife to <hi>London,</hi> hoping that change of Ayr would have done her ſome good.</p>
            <p>Third head, <hi>It was better for a man to be drunk in an Ale-houſe, then to be compelled to go to Church againſt his conſcience.</hi> Truly, there is no conſcientious man but hates drunkenneſſe, and I utterly deny that ever I ſpake ſuch words; nor was it ever in my thoughts, but in the time while I was before the Juſtices, Juſtice <hi>Hindrick</hi> demanded of me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he might not being in authority, compell a man from Ale-houſe to Church? My anſwer was, <hi>That I thought</hi> (as alſo his experience might witneſſe) <hi>that there was many a man at Church which had rather be at an Ale-houſe;</hi> wherein we did agree: Yet notwithſtanding, what the Juſtices reaſon was I know not, he himſelf did endeavou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to give a falſe interpretation of my words (ſaying) that I ſpake as Mr.
<hi>Edwards</hi> indee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did write; but before we parted, I did clear my ſelf before them; and yet Mr.
<hi>Edwards</hi> names it in his Book! which is neither wiſe nor juſt, for him to raiſe up that which was buried, and that which is not true. But I much blame (not Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi>) but his <hi>Informer</hi> who was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and if I miſtake not, a man not to be believed; for while I was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Juſtices, he pleaded againſt me for being an Independent, and yet he himſelf the next morning, ſpeaking with an honeſt Chriſtian man of the ſame Town, told him; <hi>That he did hope the Independents would have the day.</hi> Nay ſince his leaving of the ſame Town, and being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a benefice, told a Gentleman of <hi>Newbery,</hi> who was to ſeek out for an honeſt Miniſter, that he was an <hi>Independent</hi> (any thing to get a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice) I might name many things, wherein I might prove him not to be a man worthy to be believed; but love conſtraines me for the Goſpels ſake, rather to pitie and weep over him, then to ſpeak or do any thing that may conduce to his hurt, though he was a man that ſought and uſed many wayes to prejudice me; but I may ſay as the <hi>Wiſe-man</hi> ſaith, <hi>He is faln into that pit which he himſelf digged for me;</hi> he ſought to make me odious and in the end he himſelf became odious, ſo that I ſee my enemy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:159706:8"/> fall before me, inſomuch that not one in the Town would lodge him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it were the Divels Shop-houſes, as he himſelf cals them (Ale-houſes I mean) which made him to leave the Town, to whom he was then Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter; but I forbear, leaving both him and my ſelf to God, that if it be his will we may both receive his Image, whereby we may walk one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another as becommeth Brethren. So I conclude, with an humble requeſt to Mr.
<hi>Edwards,</hi> that for the time to come, he would be pleaſed to believe none, let them come with what fair pretences ſoever, though it be againſt the <hi>Independents,</hi> but what his eyes ſeeth, and his ears hear, the contrary being that which gives abuſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, to the Goſpel, in that the Profeſſors thereof ſhould take up baſe and beggarly informations one againſt another, which in theſe our days is the Goſpels reproach.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it gives abuſe to both the Honourable Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Firſt, in preſenting that unto them as Accuſations, which cannot with ſafety to the preſenter be depoſed of oath, as bare informations cannot; but I could wiſh, ſeeing he hath preſented ſo many accuſations to the Honourable Houſes, they would pleaſe to call him to depoſe it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on oath; for if nothing as an accuſation is to be given in to any inferiour Court, much leſſe into that, without it can be depoſited upon oath: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in the preſenting of theſe things to the Higheſt Court in <hi>England,</hi> where ought to be none but matters of the higheſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nature, which is not fit to be heard in an inferiour Court, nay ſuch things as will cauſe a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious heart to bluſh, and to ſtop his ear in the reading of; now that ſuch things ſhould be preſented to the Honourable Houſes, wherein are ſo many ſpirituall and gracious hearts! I hope I need not mention any one thing, but I leave the Chriſtian to the reading of his book: Now what abuſes he hath here offered to the Honourable Houſe, let all that truly love them judge?</p>
            <p>In the third place, he mightily wrongs the Cauſe, wherein thoſe that are truly cordiall to the Parliament are deeply engaged; Firſt, in giving the common enemy not onely cauſe to blaſpheme, but alſo an advantage againſt us, and this he doth, by divulging abroad to the world the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences that are amongſt: us: Secondly, he wrongs the Cauſe, which is this bleeding Kingdomes good, in that through his falſe accuſing thoſe, who are as reall for the PARLIAMENT and this Kingdomes good as himſelf (if without offence I may make compariſons) for I know that many who have done great ſervice for the Parliament and Kingdome, have diſſerted their ſervice; becauſe that while they have been fighting againſt the common enemy, they themſelves have been fought againſt by him, and others; and for their ſervice done the Parliament, they have <pb n="14" facs="tcp:159706:9"/> been (both in Pulpit &amp; Preſſe) divulg'd to the world under the names of Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, and many other ſuch like names, which have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartened many, and cauſed them to leave the ſervice; Truly, me thinks that if Mr.
<hi>Edwards</hi> was cordiall in his love towards the good of this dying Kingdome, he would have hid and covered the infirmities if he did ſee any, of thoſe who are willing to die, rather then this Kingdome or the Parliament thereof ſhould die (in the deſtroying of the common enemy) what if his honour had faln by the infirmities of thoſe who were as aforeſaid? me thinks if he had not been altogether for himſelf, but had altogether aimed and ſought after the Kingdomes good, he would willingly have loſt his honour, rather then this Kingdome and its Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould dye, in the loſing of their priviledges; which is the honour, glory, and life of both; to which the priviledge, honour, and life of one man is nothing: It's a ſad thing that a Kingdome ſhould die, Parliament die, and all becauſe we cannot paſſe by honour and others infirmities, even one of another! Oh who cannot but paſſe by all for this Kingdoms good? Nay ſad it is, that Miniſters who have taught, do not do ſo: (what will become of this dying Kingdome?) this is ſad: But this is ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, even that Brethren, for whom Chriſt died and ſhed his precious bloud, that they ſhould not hide each others infirmities, but are ready and daily do pierce tongue and pen, like Jewiſh ſpears, into each others ſides, whereby they bleed and dye by the hand one of another. Oh who cannot but mourn, in the hearing and reading railing accuſations of one brother againſt another? Chriſt laid down his life for us, that we might lay down our lives one for another: but oh, how do we dye one for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when we ſet forth railing accuſations one againſt another? Chriſt denied all, that he might bring us to all, and that when we were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: but do we deny our ſelves and all, to bring thoſe that are out of our judgement to the knowledge of the truth, whereby they may ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cloſe with us, as one with and in the truth? O no, what diſputes, what railings and heart-burnings, nay what praying is there one againſt another? ſo that whereas we ſhould ſeek after and pray one for anothers good, we pray and ſeek after the contrary (even the ruine and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction one of another) and that of Brethren: Oh who cannot but die, in the beholding one Brother die by the hands of another, for whom CHRIST died.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
